A Guide to the Virginia Department of Health Professions Historical Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Virginia Department of Health Professions Historical Collection. 1917-1986
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2005/May/12
.8 linear feet, 12 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Virginia Department of Health Professions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The collection was donated due to the historical importance of the records. These are not the offical records of the Virginia Department of Health Professions.
Scope and Content
The Board of Pharmacy records consist of historical applications, as well as photographs of confiscated drugs.
The Board of Nursing records consist of historical bylaws booklets and a report on the condition of nursing schools conducted in 1920.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Board of Pharmacy (Box-folder 2)
  - Index to Applicants for Registered Pharmacists and Registered Assistant Pharmacist 1-1500 1901-1916 (Box-folder 1.1)
    This folder contains an alphabetical listing of the first 1500 registered pharmacists regulated by the Board as well as a copy of the Seal.
  - Bankbooks from State-Planters Bank 1933-1972 (Box-folder 1.2)
    This folder contains bankbooks that list the financial security of the State Board of Pharmacy.
  - Application for Examination as Registered Pharmacist 1906 (Box-folder 1.3)
    This folder contains applications for pharmaceutical license. Each application has supporting documentation attached, like statements to work experience and character.
  - Scrapbook and photograph collection. 1942, 1959 (Box-folder 1.4)
    This folder contains several photographs and a scrapbook.
    - Members of the Board of Pharmacy 1889 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Pictured are C.B. Fleet, Robert Brydon, E. R. Beckwith, J. W. Pierce. Beckwith and Brydon were original members.
    - Scrapbook of confiscated drugs. circa 1942 (Box-folder 1.4)
      Each entry has a photograph and caption.
    - Photographs of possibly confiscated drugs. 1959 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Prescriptions collection 1921 (Box-folder 1.5)
    This folder contains several prescriptions from doctors in Salem and Roanoke, Virginia.
- Board of Nursing (Box-folder 2)
  This series consist of documents and correspondence of the Virginia Board of Nursing.
  - Rules, Bylaws, and Laws regarding Nursing and the State Board 1917-1986 (Box-folder 2.1)
    This folder contains bylaws, congressional legislation, and updates. The bulk of this folder is the yearly bylaw booklets.
  - "Report of Inspection of Training Schools of Virginia" 1920 (Box-folder 2.2)
    This folder contains the proceedings of a report of all the nurse training programs through the state. Also contains the correspondence this report created within the Schools.
  - Papers related to the operation of the Board of Nursing 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2.3)
    This folder contains various documents regarding the Board of Nursing. Included are supply order forms, lists of nursing training hospitals, and other evaluation forms.
  - Personal Correspondence. (Box-folder 2.4)
    This folder contains letters and papers of a personal nature from Ethel Smith, Julia Mellichamp, and R. V. Blankinship. All were early Board of Nursing members. Mellichamp and Smith were the first two leaders of the Board.
  - Annual and Financial Reports 1961-1967 (Box-folder 2.5)
    This folder contains the Annual and Financial reports of the Board of Nursing
  - Nursing Licensing Information. (Box-folder 2.6)
    This folder contains rules for practical nurses, licenses for Certified Tuberculosis Nurses, and a listing of Board members.
  - "First Nurse registered in Virginia" (Box-folder 2.7)
    This folder includes the paperwork on the first nurse and practical nurse to be registered in Virginia.
  - Policies and recommendations regarding nursing education. 1917-1966 (Box-folder 2.8)
    This bulk of this folder contains regulation booklets from 1917-1966 as well as a 1964 Report to the State Council n Education.
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box-folder 2.9)
    This folder contains several booklets on various subjects and concerns of the State Board.